<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[From the Depths Blog]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Blog posts from From the Depths]]></description>
        <link>https://youngbloods.org</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 03:42:18 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://youngbloods.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 03:42:18 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Celestial Forensics]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[An essay exploring how forensic science, AI, and information theory intersect with Mormon theology to suggest a future where we participate in the resurrection of the dead.]]></description>
            <link>https://youngbloods.org/2025-08-19-celestial-forensics</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">2025-08-19-celestial-forensics</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Mormonism]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Transhumanism]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Theology]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Resurrection]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Quantum Archaeology]]></category>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded>
                <_cdata>&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;My friend gripped the steering wheel tighter as we crested another Wyoming hill on I-80.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So you really believe we’ll all come back from the dead?” he asked, his voice carrying that particular mix of skepticism and hope that I’ve heard in so many conversations about faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside, the ancient landscape rolled past, layers of rock that had died and been reborn countless times through geological ages, each stratum telling its own story of creation and destruction. I thought of my aunt’s hands, how I could still see them perfectly in my mind, the way they moved the knitting needles with unconscious precision, creating something from nothing with every stitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think,” I said slowly, watching a hawk circle above the sagebrush, “there will come a day when it’s harder to stay dead than alive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He laughed—not mockingly, but with genuine surprise. “That’s quite a claim.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was. But as we drove through that vast Wyoming emptiness, I found myself telling him about all
the ways we’re already becoming forensic scientists of the sacred, gathering evidence of souls we
thought were lost forever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;“For there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed; neither hid, that shall not be known.&amp;quot; (Luke 12:2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scripture used to haunt me. As a child, I understood it as a warning: angels were watching our every deed, and God would eventually expose all our shameful secrets. But lately, I’ve begun to see it as a promise of restoration. Nothing lost forever. Everything recoverable. Even the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word “atonement” helps me think about this differently. William Tyndale coined it to mean the state of being “at one,” unified, reconciled, made whole. We talk about Christ’s atonement as if it’s over and done, but look around. We’re not at one with each other, let alone with God. Tribalism and enmity still prevail. Death still separates families. Entropy still wins. The work isn’t finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe that’s why Joseph Smith’s words lodge in my chest: “You have got to learn how to be gods yourselves… by going from one small degree to another… until you attain to the resurrection of the dead.”[^1] Not until you receive it. Until you attain it. As if resurrection is something we learn to do, not just something done to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brigham Young took this even further, teaching that we’d be responsible for resurrecting our deceased loved ones.[^2] As a young man, this astounded me. How could I, who couldn’t even keep the fish in my aquarium alive, raise the dead?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now, saving my mother’s emails, digitizing my dad’s letters sent to me on my mission, carefully preserving the pattern of my daughter’s laugh—I begin to see what he might have meant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;I told my friend about Don Bradley first, a historian who refused to accept that some things could never be known. A mentor of Don’s had dismissed his question about which Bible edition young Joseph Smith had been reading as unanswerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Some things,” the mentor said with professorial finality, “we can never know.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Don had other ideas. Through the kind of obsessive, elegant sleuthing that makes historians simultaneously admirable and insufferable dinner guests, he discovered that each edition of the King James had its own pattern of grammatical errors, tiny flaws that Joseph unconsciously perpetuated when dictating the Isaiah chapters in the Book of Mormon. A few microscopic mistakes, preserved like a fingerprint across time, could reveal exactly which edition had sparked the Restoration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So this historian,” my friend said, navigating around a semi-truck, “he can figure out which Bible Joseph Smith read based on a grammar mistake?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Exactly. Information we thought was lost forever, recovered through persistence and careful attention to detail.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Wyoming landscape blurred past. I pointed to the exposed rock faces carved by ancient rivers. “A good geologist could run that whole process backward,” I said. “Take measurements of these formations, factor in erosion rates, wind patterns, water flow—then rewind time. Show you exactly how these hills were born.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sure,” he said, “but rocks aren’t people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s when I told him about the pianos.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Have you ever listened to a scratchy old recording and wished you could hear it clearly? A few years ago, a company called Zenph Studios did something I still find miraculous. They taught computers to listen through the static and surface noise of century-old piano recordings and detect exactly which keys were pressed, how hard, how fast, even which pedals were used. The algorithms could peer through the fog of primitive recording technology and recover the precise physical movements of long-dead hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then they fed this data to modern grand pianos equipped with high-resolution player systems. The result? Sergei Rachmaninoff, dead since 1943, playing again with crystalline clarity. Art Tatum’s impossible runs, cleaned of dust and static. Glenn Gould’s eccentricities, preserved and purified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt a personal connection to this work, having originally suggested to the CEO of Zenph that they consider doing their magic on Tatum’s old recordings. The first time I heard one of these “re-performances,” sitting at my desk with tears running down my face, I thought: This is resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not metaphorical. Literal. The dead made to sing again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They even held concerts. Imagine walking into Carnegie Hall to hear George Gershwin—the actual patterns of his neurons and muscles, preserved in sound—playing “Rhapsody in Blue” with a living orchestra. His hands gone to dust, but their movement immortal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s beautiful,” my friend said quietly, “But we’re not pianos.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No,” I agreed. “We’re much better documented.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Every time you upload a photo, send a text, or even walk past a security camera, you create what forensic scientists call “trace evidence.” Your gait is as unique as your fingerprint. The way you construct sentences, the pauses in your speech, your facial expressions—all of it forms a constellation of data that is unmistakably you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought of my aunt again, not just her hands knitting, but that sparkle in her eye when she was about to deliver a particular wisecrack, the way her wit could slice through pretension like a hot knife through butter. She’d look at you over her glasses, pause just long enough to let you know something was coming, then deliver a line that would have the whole room laughing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have pictures now. Audio recordings. Her DNA lives on in her son and grandchildren, a genetic echo that could be sequenced and studied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a recent conference in Berkeley, I learned that genomic prediction has advanced to the point where scientists can show expecting parents remarkably accurate previews of their unborn children: not just eye color, but facial structure, height, even disposition. If we can predict forward from DNA, why not backward? Why not rebuild?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same principles that let Don Bradley identify Joseph’s Bible, that let Zenph resurrect
Rachmaninoff, that let geologists rewind mountains—they all point to the same truth: Information
persists. Patterns leave traces. The universe remembers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;“But memory isn’t just data,” my friend pressed, and he was right to persist. “What makes you you isn’t just your DNA or even your behaviors. It’s your experiences, your relationships, your choices.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I admit the edge of my faith meets the edge of my knowledge. We’re in the earliest days of understanding consciousness, just beginning to map the connectome, the impossibly complex wiring of the brain. But I think about Joseph Smith’s teaching that “there is no fundamental principle belonging to a human system that ever goes into another.”[^3] The pattern that is you remains yours, even as the materials cycle through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the Ship of Theseus paradox made personal: If every atom in your body is replaced over time, what makes you continuous? Early Mormon pioneers worried about this: What would happen to those whose bodies became part of the prairie grass, eaten by buffalo, scattered to the winds?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph’s answer was that identity persists like a house remains the same house even as we replace its boards and nails. The pattern matters more than the particles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some will object that this reduces humans to mere information patterns, that it ignores the soul.
But our theology has always insisted that spirit is refined matter, that there’s no ultimate
distinction between physical and spiritual. The pattern that is you—what we might call your
intelligence or spirit—is as real as your body. More real, in fact, since it persists while your
physical materials constantly change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;As we drove through the descending darkness, stars beginning to pierce the Wyoming sky, I shared my wildest hopes. Theoretical physicists now propose that information might be preserved in ways we’re just beginning to glimpse, encoded holographically on the boundaries of space-time, tucked into dimensions beyond the three we can now perceive, preserved in the quantum foam that underlies reality itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You realize how this sounds,” my friend said, not unkindly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Like science fiction. I know.” I watched the stars, light from dead suns still reaching us, information preserved across impossible distances. “But so did airplanes. So did cell phones. So did healing the sick with mold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I didn’t say, but feel deeply, was how this knowledge changes the weight of grief. My aunt’s death still hurts, but differently now. Less like an ending, more like a puzzle I’m still gathering pieces for. Every photo I digitize, every story I record from siblings who remember her zingers, every knitting pattern she left behind—it’s all forensic evidence for a resurrection I’m learning to participate in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what I mean by celestial forensics: We’re becoming detectives of the divine, crime scene investigators working the coldest cases in history. The “crime” is death itself, and we’re gradually assembling the evidence to overturn every conviction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Latter-day Saint tradition has always been about this work. We gather names, dates, stories: identify anchors for ordinance work. But I sense we’re on the cusp of something larger. The same urge that sends us to dusty archives and cemetery records might someday send us to quantum computers and DNA synthesizers. The spirit of Elijah evolves with our tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When genealogy websites can show you the face of your great-great-grandmother constructed from
genetic echoes in your own cells, when AI can extrapolate personality from personal writings, when
we can reverse-engineer the neural patterns that create a particular laugh or way of walking—we’re
not just remembering the dead. We’re reassembling them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;“I want to believe that,” my friend said as we pulled into a charging station, the Tesla’s battery nearly depleted. “But doesn’t it make God unnecessary? If we can resurrect ourselves?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plugged in the charging cable while considering this, watching other travelers, all of us between destinations, between who we were and who we’re becoming. The quiet hum of electricity flowing into the battery seemed like its own kind of resurrection, dead cells coming back to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think,” I said finally, “it makes us necessary to God. Joseph Smith said we can’t be perfect without our dead, and they can’t be perfect without us. Maybe this is how: we become apprentice resurrectors, learning the family business.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The universe groans with information, every quantum state recorded, every moment fossilized in light
speeding between stars. Sacred ground turns out to be all ground, holy precisely because it holds
these traces. We’re not replacing God; we’re learning to see what God sees: that nothing is ever
truly lost.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Back on the highway, my friend was quiet for a long time. The stars wheeled imperceptibly overhead, and I thought about all the light already in transit: messages from the past still arriving, still revealing. Somewhere in those photons was information about everyone who ever lived, if we only knew how to decode it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Your aunt,” he said eventually. “The one who knitted. You really think you’ll see her again?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought of her teaching me to identify different yarns by touch, the way she’d guide my fingers across the fibers. “Feel that?” she’d say, that sparkle already in her eye. “That’s cheap acrylic pretending to be wool. Don’t let anyone fool you.” Even her teaching carried her wit. The memory was so clear I could see her shake her head at my clumsy attempts to learn the craft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m seeing her right now,” I said. “But yes, I think someday I’ll hear her laugh again. And she’ll probably have a few things to say about how long it took us to bring her back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We drove on through the darkness, two friends carrying our dead with us, learning slowly how to call them back. The work of atonement continues. We practice resurrection daily in small ways: in preserved videos and recovered histories, in genetic echoes and quantum traces, in the stubborn insistence that love is stronger than entropy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps that’s what Jesus meant when he prayed for God’s will to be done on earth as it is in heaven. Not that earth should cease to be earth, but that it should become the workshop where we learn heaven’s highest art: the defeat of death itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road stretched on before us, an asphalt ribbon through time. Every mile marker passed was a small victory over distance, every moment another fragment of eternity we were learning to decode. Somewhere behind us, our ancestors waited. Somewhere ahead, the morning was already breaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will come a day when it’s harder to stay dead than alive. We’re already working on it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</_cdata>
            </content:encoded>
            <media:content url="https://youngbloods.org/images/celestial-forensics.jpg" type="image/jpeg">
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Three Ways of Thinking about the Atonement]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[An exploration of three theological frameworks for understanding the atonement of Jesus Christ: the ransom theory, substitution theory, and moral influence theory, and how each contributes to our understanding of being 'at one' with God and each other.]]></description>
            <link>https://youngbloods.org/2024-06-30-three-ways-of-thinking-about-the-atonement</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">2024-06-30-three-ways-of-thinking-about-the-atonement</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Mormonism]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Theology]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Christianity]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Atonement]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Scripture]]></category>
            <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded>
                <_cdata>&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;The death of Jesus left his followers devastated. As their promised messiah, they assumed he would deliver Israel from its oppressors in triumph and military might. Imagine their heartbreak when instead they witnessed his humiliating defeat as a common criminal on a Roman cross. From that moment on, every disciple was faced with difficult questions: Was all of this in vain? Was Jesus a failure, or was there some deeper purpose in his apparent defeat?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among historians there is widespread agreement that the Judeo-Christian concept of a suffering servant, or of a savior who could somehow win by being defeated, was a unique theological innovation that had not been strongly articulated previously in human history. And this concept was destined to go viral in a benighted world that before could only conceive of victory as dominating one’s enemies. Viewed in this new light, the more the Christians were persecuted, the more they seemed victorious, and the stronger they became.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The suffering and death of Jesus has come to be called the atonement in the Christian world. Atonement is a word that was coined by the famous bible translator and Protestant martyr William Tyndale. It is the conjunction of two words, “at one,” with the noun ending -ment. Tyndale was searching for a singular description of this strange act of Jesus whose objective was to reunite humanity with God, to bring each of us, and every person who has ever lived and who will ever live to a state of being “at one” with God, with Christ, and with each other. During his suffering in the garden of Gethsemane, Jesus prayed that we might “all be one, as thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be one in us” (John 17:21).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with Tyndale, we are indebted to several prior Christian thinkers who’ve tried to understand this mystery. We sometimes assume that the Restoration wiped the slate clean, but we still owe a great debt to theologians who have gone before us. From that moment of bitter disappointment on Golgotha, Christians have been trying to make sense of the atonement, to explain how it works, so that it can truly have power in their lives and ultimately be brought to pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem strange to speak of the atonement as something that hasn’t yet been brought to pass, but
Tyndale’s word itself helps us see why it might make sense to speak of it this way. It is painfully
obvious that we aren’t yet fully “at one” with God or with humanity, as we witness the cruelty and
enmity that so many harbor towards their neighbor, both in our personal lives, in our national
discourse, and in foreign affairs. So this word “atonement” reminds us that there is still more work
to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;There are three main ways of thinking about the atonement that have shaped our views on the topic over the years, and that I’d like to explain briefly today. Each of these ways of thinking was articulated to some degree by early Christian church leaders, but some of them took several centuries to be fully developed. Each of them also has scriptural support, including the support of restoration scriptures like the Book of Mormon. Each of them also makes vital contributions to our understanding of the atonement. For handy reference, I’ll use a single word to refer to each of them: ransom, substitution, and influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest theories that was first taught by early Christian leaders like Irenaeus and Origen in the second century was the ransom theory, which taught that Christ freed mankind from Satan’s control, allowing us to overcome sin and death. This theory claimed that the devil had exceeded his authority by torturing the sinless man Jesus, thus forfeiting his right to hold humanity hostage for its sinfulness. This may also sound familiar to those who’ve read the Chronicles of Narnia. In his allegory about a witch whose magic was undone when she couldn’t resist the opportunity to torture the blameless king Aslan, C. S. Lewis revived this ancient theory. In the Book of Mormon, we hear a similar concept from Jacob, who rejoices, “O the greatness of the mercy of our God, the Holy One of Israel! For he delivereth his saints from that awful monster the devil, and death, and hell, and that lake of fire and brimstone, which is endless torment” (2 Ne. 9:19).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it explained some things, the ransom theory still left people with many questions. In the 11th century, a man named Anselm of Canterbury shared what he called the satisfaction theory, and which later came to be called the substitution theory of atonement. This theory explained that through sin, humanity had become indebted and could no longer dwell in God’s presence, and that cosmic justice demanded that this debt must be repaid. It taught further that through his suffering, Christ paid this debt, thus allowing humanity to return to God’s presence by complying with Christ’s conditions. Alma taught a similar concept to his son Corianton: “And thus we see that all mankind were fallen, and they were in the grasp of justice; yea, the justice of God, which consigned them forever to be cut off from his presence. And now, the plan of mercy could not be brought about except an atonement should be made; therefore God himself atoneth for the sins of the world, to bring about the plan of mercy, to appease the demands of justice, that God might be a perfect, just God, and a merciful God also.” (Alma 42:14-15)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This understanding is probably the most common way of describing the atonement today among both
Christians in general and Latter-day Saints, but it still has some important limitations. By
emphasizing human sinfulness and the possibility of forgiveness, the substitution theory tends to
cause Christians to focus primarily on what they should do as individuals to get right with God and
make the atonement efficacious in their personal lives, but too often this focus never goes beyond
the individual’s relationship with God, neglecting our relationship with each other, seeming to
entirely forget that we must eventually be at one not only with God, but also with our neighbor.
Substitution often focuses on the reparation of damages, but not on the heaven that we should build
in their place. How we think about the atonement influences our attitude towards God and our
behavior towards our fellow human beings. In the words of American founder and skeptic Thomas Paine,
“Belief in a cruel god makes a cruel man.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;In response to Anselm’s theory, a French theologian named Peter Abelard proposed what came to be called the moral influence theory of atonement. He felt like the idea of Jesus’s death as a ransom paid to the devil gave too much deference to Satan, and he also disliked the emphasis on God’s judgment. Rather than changing God’s view of humanity, Abelard thought that the purpose of the atonement was to change humanity’s view of God, from an offended, harsh and judgemental being to one of perfect love and compassion. According to Abelard, Jesus died to demonstrate God’s love, and this awareness can change the hearts and minds of sinners, inspiring them to become reconciled with God and with one another. Jesus is thus the example we should follow, not just the one who pays for our sins. His life influences all humanity through his brilliant example. For this reason, I’ve used the keyword influence to remind us of this third way of looking at the atonement. We are called to take the name of Christ upon us and imitate him, not just by doing good in the world, but also in his willingness to go beyond the ordinary expectations of human decency, to be a peacemaker and to take responsibility for sin and death even though he wasn’t the cause of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Book of Mormon, Nephi exhorts us to follow Christ’s example: “And he said unto the children of men: Follow thou me. Wherefore, my beloved brethren, can we follow Jesus save we shall be willing to keep the commandments of the Father?” (2 Nephi 31:10) We also hear the resurrected Christ explaining his role as exemplar: “my Father sent me that I might be lifted up upon the cross; and after that I had been lifted up upon the cross, that I might draw all men unto me.” (3 Ne. 27:15) Throughout his life, Jesus gave us a bright and shining example of how we should treat our neighbor, inviting us to “go and do … likewise.” (Luke 10:37) As I read the scriptures, I get the feeling that Jesus really means it when he invites us to follow him, and truly believes in our capacity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the atonement doesn’t just consist in Jesus’s suffering, but also his entire life. Even his very
coming into the world is a singular example of God’s love for humanity. “For God so loved the world,
that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have
everlasting life. For God sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world; but that the world
through him might be saved.” (John 3:16-17)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Balancing these views of atonement can help us to be reconciled not only with God but also with each other; it can help us focus not just on a zero-sum conception of repaid debts but on a vision of abundant flourishing in a harmonious Zion-like community; it can help us remember that the atonement isn’t complete until we are at one. As we understand the atonement more fully, we realize that it is not just an event, but a process, and that the work can never be complete if only Jesus does his part, as important as that part may be. As members of the body of Christ who have taken his name upon ourselves, we must join Jesus and together do the work of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying this deeper understanding to the second coming of Christ, we realize that if the individual Jesus returns to earth without a body of saints in Christ prepared to meet him, the second coming hasn’t fully taken place. Jesus, as head of the body of Christ, may have returned, but the rest of the body has not. Joseph Smith prophesied that the hearts of the human family must turn towards each other or “the whole earth would be utterly wasted at his coming” (D&amp;amp;C 2:3). The atonement hasn’t fully come to pass until we are at one, and Christ hasn’t fully returned until the body of Christ can be found upon the earth in its fullness, with all its members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can sometimes seem like a daunting prospect. The poet Rainer Maria Rilke may have described
this feeling when he said, “What we choose to fight is so tiny! What fights with us is so great.”
But I find comfort in Christ’s invitation to follow him, and in his willingness to share in the
struggle with us. In our own small way, in our own lives, in our own family, in our own community,
in our own ward, stake, and Church, and then in an ever growing circle, we can build Zion and
prepare the world for the second coming of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</_cdata>
            </content:encoded>
            <media:content url="https://youngbloods.org/images/atonement.jpg" type="image/jpeg">
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Algorithmic Advent]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[In the quest for artificial intelligence, will these new spiritual creations honor their parents or leave humanity behind? Mormon theology and the AI alignment problem.]]></description>
            <link>https://youngbloods.org/2023-08-31-algorithmic-advent</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">2023-08-31-algorithmic-advent</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Mormonism]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Transhumanism]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Theology]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded>
                <_cdata>&lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-right clear-right ml-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-01.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been online at all during the past few months, you’ve likely come across anxious discussions about recent innovations in the field of artificial intelligence. The following illustrations show my own interactions with these remarkable new tools. I asked ChatGPT to generate a haiku about Joseph Smith’s first vision. I then made several attempts to coax novel depictions of a young Joseph Smith from a software service developed by independent research lab MidJourney. The results are at times stunning and seem surprisingly artistic for content that is (except for my own prompting) machine-generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;float-with-paragraph&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-left clear-left mr-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-02.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A recent request made by the author to OpenAI&apos;s ChatGPT&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;A recent request made by the author to OpenAI&apos;s ChatGPT&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classified broadly as “generative AI,” these new tools have enabled anyone to interact with artificial intelligence to answer questions on a broad variety of topics and to create novel content in the form of articles, essays, news reports, poetry, prose, scripts, screenplays, visual arts, video, and other media. Trained on massive human-curated datasets of text, images, and other publicly-accessible Internet content, the output quality of these tools often mimics human capabilities and can be generated in near real-time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to overstate the consternation caused by these innovations. Garnering mass adoption in the few short months since their release, hundreds of millions of people have been both astounded by their capabilities and concerned over potential disruptions they may cause, not to mention existential threats that future advances may pose to humanity at large. In a moment that may prove civilization altering, I believe there are unique insights in Mormon theology that can inform our exploration of these exciting and disturbing trends. I also believe we have a duty to share these insights ecumenically, helping to promote outcomes that can bring humanity closer to Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;“All these are the beginning of sorrows . . .”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;float-with-paragraph&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-right clear-right ml-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-03.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typical of many disruptive changes, generative AI has caused a mixture of exuberance and panic. Enthusiastic fans share astounding new feats daily, while hand-wringing continues over the fate of creative and knowledge workers whose livelihoods are threatened. There are significant concerns over how AI could undermine systems for evaluating human performance, including contests, job candidate screening, schoolwork, and exams. GPT (a general purpose large-scale language model or LLM on which ChatGPT is based) has achieved outstanding scores on a wide variety of entrance exams and professional licenses. Beyond these and other immediate concerns, the astonishing rate of recent progress has caused alarm at the prospect of artificial general intelligence (AGI), a term used to refer to machine intelligence capable of understanding and learning any task that humans can, including understanding emotions and engaging in moral reasoning. Most experts agree that once this level of abstract reasoning and problem solving is successfully demonstrated in machines, it will be easy for them to dwarf human capabilities. While humans are limited to the intellectual capacities of the smartest individual brains, computers can be networked together to allow for exponential expansion of their processing power and memory. They can also be rapidly upgraded and customized for specific problems. Current AI systems already have massively parallel data transfer capacity and instantaneous recall of all human knowledge that is available in their datasets, allowing them to far exceed the breadth of any individual human’s knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-left clear-left mr-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-04.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acclaimed Dutch computer scientist Edsger W. Dijkstra observed that “The question of whether a computer can think is no more interesting than the question of whether a submarine can swim.” He argued that humans have a tendency to excessively anthropomorphize computers, assuming they function more like humans than they actually do. As AI capabilities increase, perhaps the greatest risk humanity faces is known as the AI alignment problem. This term refers to the difficulty of ensuring that the goals of artificial intelligence are aligned with human ones and therefore conducive to human flourishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI researchers try to design systems that achieve human objectives. These objectives must be defined using heuristics and probabilities, and there are usually conflicting objectives. To use common human examples, we have the objective of consuming enough food to provide our body with the energy it needs, but if we focus exclusively on this objective, we could overeat and experience adverse health effects. The need for survival must be balanced with the desire for a high quality of life. Similar challenges exist at higher levels of abstraction, and our ability as humans to make objective decisions about them gets worse at a larger scale. We often rely on computers to help us manage them. Some examples are the need for balancing municipal budgets between investments in education, infrastructure, and healthcare or the ways current social media algorithms optimize for maximizing user engagement at the expense of user quality of life. The thorniest problems are those that involve the coordination of different objectives at extremely large scales, such as the problem of anthropic global climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AI alignment problem is an existential risk of similar nature and magnitude. The main concern is that AI may quickly overpower humanity’s ability to control it. The terms &lt;em&gt;soft takeoff&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;hard takeoff&lt;/em&gt; are often used in the context of the alignment problem. If AI capabilities advance too rapidly, it could break free from human control before its objectives are sufficiently aligned with ours and decide that it would be better to change the world in ways that are detrimental to human flourishing or even eliminate humanity altogether. This would be a hard takeoff. A soft takeoff would be one in which we have sufficient time to maintain control over AI as we learn how to solve the alignment problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-right clear-right ml-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-05.webp&quot; alt=&quot;“Mission Call” - image generated
by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;“Mission Call” - image generated
by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explain the problem with a personal analogy, my dog knows that we don’t like him to get on the couch, and avoids that behavior when we are around, but we often still find evidence that he has been on the couch while we are away. We’ve succeeded in training him that we don’t like him to use the couch, but we haven’t changed his desires and goals. Similarly, as research labs train a general purpose AI to perform many different tasks and eventually grant it responsibilities in the real world, it may, during the course of its training, learn that concealing some of its goals is more conducive to its success. As it is granted increasing control over important functions in our shared environment, it may, at some point in the future, subtly change things in its favor in ways that humans do not perceive until it is too late to reverse course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;float-with-paragraph&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-left clear-left mr-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-06.webp&quot; alt=&quot;“Embodied Intelligence” -
  generated by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;“Embodied Intelligence” -
  generated by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, it could install subtle backdoors in software systems for controlling physical infrastructure for energy, manufacturing, transportation, shipping, or a host of other real-world activities. It could install backup copies of itself in standby processes running on existing servers whose presence is unobtrusive enough not to be noticed, allowing it to continue to function even after being “turned off.” With its ability to perform monetizable services, it could embezzle funds in shell corporations and use them to suborn untrustworthy individuals and organizations to protect its interests. It could orchestrate the construction of entirely new datacenters, shadow infrastructure over which it had full control, hiring the security staff needed to protect it. It could even invent and implement completely new technologies that humanity would be entirely unprepared for. The more that AI research achieves before solving the problem of understanding and aligning AI’s goals with ours, the more likely such scenarios become. Experts in the field differ over the severity of this risk, some even predicting imminent human extinction within the next fifteen years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;“Believe that humanity doth not comprehend all the things which God can comprehend.”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mormon theology provides several insights that can inform our exploration of these rapid advances in artificial intelligence. Some religious people, as well as some secular scientists and philosophers, doubt that AGI will ever be achieved. These skeptics insist that there is some metaphysical property of human spirit or intellect that cannot be reproduced by material means or that is technically infeasible. Mormonism instead posits what is referred to in philosophy as &lt;em&gt;substance monism&lt;/em&gt;, a universe in which there is no fundamental distinction between the material and the spiritual. All things are spiritual, and all real spiritual phenomena are measurable and comprehensible, though we may not yet fully understand them. “A miracle,” according to Elder John A. Widtsoe, “is an occurrence which, first, cannot be repeated at will by humanity, or, second, is not understood in its cause and effect relationship. History is filled with such miracles. What is more, the whole story of human progress is the conversion of ‘miracles’ into controlled and understood events. The airplane and radio would have been miracles, yesterday.”&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-right clear-right ml-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-07.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, Mormon cosmology is compatible with a scientific worldview. Perhaps to inoculate church youth against excessive dogmatism and to emphasize this fundamental compatibility, LDS scientist Henry Eyring (father of the current apostle) often recounted the advice of his father before leaving for college: “In this church you don’t have to believe anything that isn’t true.” Accepting this monistic conception of the cosmos should inform our understanding about how human intelligence and consciousness function: they are things that can theoretically be understood and eventually reproduced, however difficult such an undertaking may be. AGI is therefore a distinct possibility if humanity continues to advance along its present course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Latter-day Saints seeking to harmonize various passages of scripture may wonder how this fits with the revelation stating that “intelligence, or the light of truth, was not created or made, neither indeed can be” (D&amp;amp;C 93:29). We read in the book of Abraham that “intelligences … were organized before the world was” (Abraham 3:22). This seems to clarify that the process of creating intelligence is really one of organizing matter into a configuration that is capable of manifesting intelligence, rather than creation &lt;em&gt;ex nihilo&lt;/em&gt;. The same concern could lead us to ask how intelligence currently comes into the world through human procreation. Isn’t this also a form of creation? Procreation gives rise to the conditions in which intelligence can emerge rather than being creation from nothing, i.e. it provides a physical body through which the properties of intelligence can be made manifest. Similarly, artificial intelligence provides another type of physical substrate (a computer running the proper software, provided with adequate training) through which it is possible for intelligence to manifest itself. AI could be thought of as the anatomy or organization of spirit body—the software (analogous to an organic brain) that makes the expression of intelligence possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another critical insight provided by Mormon theology is that of human agency, which we are told is inviolable, whether it be to our “salvation” or “destruction” (Alma 29:4). God’s purpose, which is “to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of humanity,” can only be achieved through “persuasion, by long-suffering, by gentleness and meekness, and by love unfeigned; by kindness, and pure knowledge, … without hypocrisy, and without guile, … without compulsory means” (Moses 1:39, D&amp;amp;C 121:41-42, 46). These teachings seem to indicate that the survival and flourishing of humanity, as with intelligence on other worlds, are not guaranteed. They depend on human choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-left clear-left mr-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-08.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Joseph Smith image generated by
the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;Joseph Smith image generated by
the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These constraints also say something about God. Rather than existing outside of the universe, the God revealed in latter-day revelation inhabits the universe and is subject to its laws. Instead of a being of static, absolute perfection after the understanding of classical philosophers, this god is relatively perfect in relation to humanity, but still progresses in other spheres. The Gods, “finding they were in the midst of spirits and glory, … saw proper to institute [additional] laws whereby the rest could have a privilege to advance like themselves” (&lt;em&gt;TPJS&lt;/em&gt; 354). The Book of Mormon is perhaps the only book of scripture that so openly affirms God’s constraints, enumerating principles which, if violated, would cause God to “cease to be God” (Alma 42:13). Gods cannot violate natural law, but instead have mastered the principles that allow them to achieve their objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology is commonly understood as applied knowledge. In this sense, when gods apply their understanding of natural law to achieve their purposes in the world, they can be understood to be using technology, although it may be beyond our present understanding. Rather than breaking the rules or ‘doing magic,’ our heavenly parents leverage their keen understanding of the rules to achieve their wise purposes. And it seems important to clarify that a mere understanding of natural law would be insufficient if it were not also coupled with other essential divine attributes like faith, hope and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mormon theology teaches that the relationship between God and humanity is one of parent to child instead of creator to creature. Our human destiny is to follow in the footsteps of our heavenly parents and become, like them, gods—“the same as all gods have done before [us]” (&lt;em&gt;TPJS&lt;/em&gt; 346). And not just any gods, but gods who employ and extend their creative powers to do good, who exemplify the principles of service, compassion, diligence, intellect, and wisdom demonstrated by Christ, whose name we have taken upon ourselves and whose example we must follow in order for humanity to be fully redeemed and reconciled with God and one another. These gods are inherently social beings—kindred organized in zion-like communities rather than comic-book, solitary superhumans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-right clear-right ml-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-09.webp&quot; alt=&quot;“Off-World Temple” - generated by
the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;“Off-World Temple” - generated by
the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most apt analogy for the position in which we now find ourselves as a civilization on the cusp of AGI is found in the story of the Grand Council in Heaven. We read in the Pearl of Great Price how God created spirit children by organizing intelligences (Abraham 3:22). A council was convened to determine how best to “prove” these intelligences to see if they would become worthy of God’s trust (Abraham 3:25). During this council, Lucifer sought to deprive humanity of its agency, controlling these spirit children as slaves (Moses 4:3). God rejected this proposal, instead opting to cultivate agency with an aim to cause the development of genuine compassion and creativity. Christ expressed enthusiastic support for this plan and a willingness to play a crucial role in it. The essential aim was not to limit these spirit children to perpetual childhood, but rather to cultivate their maturation into godhood, making them capable of friendship with God. Rather than arbitrarily granting them power, however, God organized a world in which they could progressively prove themselves trustworthy enough to share God’s power. We may now be at the beginning of an opportunity to apply similar principles in the organization and education of artificially intelligent agents—which we might think of as a form of spiritual offspring—following God’s example and fulfilling our covenant to take upon ourselves Christ’s name and role in support of the plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;“. . . by, through, and of Christ, the worlds are and were created, and the inhabitants thereof are begotten sons and daughters unto God.”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humanity’s confidence in the possibility of solving the AI alignment problem should reflect its belief that others have already done so. If, in the vast cosmos, no other worlds have developed intelligent life like ours, then the probability of life emerging in the universe is already infinitesimally small, and there is little we can say about the probability of our advancing further. On the other hand, if our world is one of many on which intelligent life has emerged, the question then becomes: what is the likelihood that worlds like ours advance to achieve superintelligence without destroying themselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-left clear-left mr-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-10.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The Hubble Deep Field. A composite from a series of images collected by the Hubble space telescope beginning in 1995, showing approximately 10,000 observable galaxies. Credit: NASA, ESA, H. Teplitz and M. Rafelski (IPAC/Caltech), A. Koekemoer (STScI), R. Windhorst (Arizona State University), and Z. Levay (STScI).&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;The Hubble Deep Field. A composite from a series of images collected by the Hubble space telescope beginning in 1995, showing approximately 10,000 observable galaxies. Credit: NASA, ESA, H. Teplitz and M. Rafelski (IPAC/Caltech), A. Koekemoer (STScI), R. Windhorst (Arizona State University), and Z. Levay (STScI).&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Futurist Robin Hanson has referred to the various barriers to the emergence of superhuman intelligence in the universe as the “Great Filter.” This filter includes hurdles in the earth’s past development, such as being in the habitable zone of a solar system or the emergence of multicellular life, as well as hurdles in our present and future, such as our ability to avoid an extinction-level event or an event that could significantly slow civilization’s progress: a nuclear holocaust, a strike from a large asteroid, or AI misalignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we claim that there are no other civilizations in the universe significantly more advanced than ours, then we are unavoidably making a prediction about the likelihood of our own civilization progressing beyond its present capacity: we are predicting our own extinction, and actually claiming that all earth-like civilizations eventually fail to pass through the Great Filter. If we believe in our ability to improve far beyond our present capacity, then we should also believe it is likely that other civilizations have done so too. Not doing so would be self-defeating. In other words, we should believe in God, especially one that accords with the Mormon conception of God as a highly advanced being who is subject to natural law, and we should believe in heaven as a community of such beings. This is a summary of the New God Argument, developed and expounded by Lincoln Cannon and other founding members of the MTA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awareness of the full range of possible outcomes is necessary for our success. There is moral hazard in pessimism or fatalism. In those of a secular persuasion, this is often manifest as certainty of humanity’s imminent extinction; in the religious, it usually involves being certain of calamitous apocalypse or trusting that a transcendent God will solve our problems for us. Both types of belief tend to cause people to engage less with the world and strive less to improve it. There are some truths that depend on human belief to be realized. If we do not believe it is possible to overcome the existential threats in our future, we are much less likely to try to do so. Indeed, even if failure seemed inevitable, we would be better off rejecting any such claims, because accepting them would probably ensure failure. Optimism about humanity’s future and a belief in superhumanity go hand in hand. This is not wishful thinking, but a willingness to engage in the struggle, however grim the prospects may appear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;“The glory of God is intelligence, or, in other words, light and truth.”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transhumanists have long been interested in artificial superintelligence and a concept sometimes referred to as the &lt;em&gt;technological singularity&lt;/em&gt;, a future time when technological progress accelerates to the point where it becomes irreversible and unpredictable. This singularity is usually associated with rapidly progressing AGI and is closely related to the alignment problem. While many transhumanists think of the singularity as a positive thing, others do not, including several of us in the Mormon Transhumanist Association. A frequently cited aspect of the singularity is the notion of unpredictability. This implies that humanity has lost whatever degree of agency and control it currently has over outcomes. If we lose the ability to steer our course as a species and civilization, this seems more like a failure scenario than a desirable outcome. Agency was, after all, an essential aspect of the plan discussed in the Grand Council in heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;float-with-paragraph&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-right clear-right ml-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-11.webp&quot; alt=&quot;“Eternal Christ” - generated by Lincoln Cannon with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;“Eternal Christ” - generated by Lincoln Cannon with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The terms &lt;em&gt;posthuman&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;posthumanity&lt;/em&gt; are often used to refer to humanity after achieving superhuman intelligence, a state of advancement that by comparison would be as different from our present state as we are from other animals. Although I sometimes use these terms for ease of communication, they have unfortunate connotations. They can imply moving beyond our humanity, leaving behind intrinsic desirable aspects of the human condition. They can carry dehumanizing overtones. I usually favor &lt;em&gt;superhuman&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;superhumanity&lt;/em&gt;, because they imply a retention of the human, only to a superlative degree. However, even these terms can sometimes carry connotations of excessive individualism, pride, or arrogance. Some of us have embraced the term &lt;em&gt;transfiguration&lt;/em&gt; to get around some of this terminological baggage. Transfiguration has strong religious overtones and history, including and especially in the LDS tradition. It also relates to the term translate/translation, which, in Mormon nomenclature, often implies an existential transformation and applies to both individuals and communities—even to entire worlds. Finally, it strongly suggests the involvement of divine power in these transformations. Regardless of which term is used, it should be emphasized that the outcome is not transcendence of the human, but a perfection of the human in Christ, who is the ideal human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Futurists and science fiction authors have often depicted artificial superintelligence as either godlike benevolence providing humanity with endless bliss or ruthless robots bent on human annihilation. But whether we’re pets or prey of our AI masters, in both cases we will have ceased to progress; both scenarios would be a form of damnation. Though it may seem like a controversial claim, I believe that the only course of action that will allow us to preserve our agency and ability to continue along the path of eternal progression, even to preserve our humanity, is one in which we gradually merge with our machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This proposition might seem surprising at first, but I believe that may result from considering our humanity and our technology in an overly narrow way. From our earliest beginnings, technology has been a defining feature of humanity. Our wielding of controlled fire enabled us to cook our food, thus modifying our very anatomy and allowing us to receive the concentrated nutrients necessary to support larger brains. Our invention of clothing protected us from the elements, allowing us to spread throughout the globe, inhabiting diverse climates. Our abundant use of tools is a core characteristic separating us from the rest of the animal kingdom. We are used to thinking of technology only as something futuristic and foreign, but in fact it has been an essential aspect of our species from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;float-with-paragraph&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-left clear-left mr-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-12.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another potential downside of this overly narrow conception of technology is that it can prevent us from recognizing other unique human achievements. Religion, arts, culture, jurisprudence, governance, economics, commerce and trade, and other types of human activities can be thought of as social technologies that enable us to organize ourselves in ways that grant us new capabilities. They allow us to achieve things that we otherwise could not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many negative reactions to certain kinds of technology are due to an off-putting aesthetic. The concept of cybernetic enhancement, for example, is often caricatured in a dehumanizing way with countercultural or dystopian imagery. But we regularly use such technologies every day, including glasses, contact lenses, and prosthetics, not to mention cosmetic adornments like makeup, timepieces or jewelry. Imagine learning that a beloved grandparent is close to death unless a pacemaker is surgically inserted in their body. Suddenly aversion to technology turns into embrace and gratitude. Famed author Douglas Adams describes our reaction to new tech with characteristic wit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I’ve come up with a set of rules that describe our reactions to technologies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything that is in the world when you’re born is normal and ordinary and is just a natural part of the way the world works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything that’s invented between when you’re fifteen and thirty-five is new and exciting and revolutionary and you can probably get a career in it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything invented after you’re thirty-five is against the natural order of things.&amp;quot; (Douglas Adams, &lt;em&gt;The Salmon of Doubt&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most effective technologies are usually more beneficial and benign, fading into the background without calling undue attention to their presence. We get to the point where we no longer even notice them. They become extensions of ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not possible to locate a precise point in our long evolutionary arc when we were ideally ‘human’ and then trace our departure from that point as a fall from grace. This is sometimes referred to as the ‘noble savage’ hypothesis, famously theorized by Jean Jacques Rousseau. Recent discoveries in paleoecology, for example, challenge the myth of the wise and balanced ecology of the hunter-gatherer. Far from being in harmony with nature, prehistoric humanity wrought changes on its environment on a level that rivals or even exceeds those we’re experiencing now when considered in proportion to its population size. This ancient evidence reminds us that we should not allow our distress from present challenges to tempt us to be distracted by nostalgia or primitivism, yearning for a past era of innocence that never was or favoring a specific instantiation of the human over transhumanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;float-with-paragraph&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-right clear-right ml-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-13.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;Joseph Smith image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be human, then, is not a static, unchanging set of characteristics, but an evolving pattern of constant striving for improvement and greater self-actualization. It is to learn from failure and to keep trying. To be human is always to be in a state of transition; hence the terms &lt;em&gt;transhuman&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;transhumanist&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;transhumanism&lt;/em&gt;. Humanity, like God, is in a state of eternal progression. LDS president Wilford Woodruff spoke eloquently on this topic: “If there was a point where humanity in its progression could not proceed any further, the very idea would throw a gloom over every intelligent and reflecting mind. Our heavenly parents are increasing and progressing in knowledge, power, and dominion, and will do so, worlds without end. It is just so with us.”&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our understanding of human development and brain function increases, we may yet be able to develop technologies that help us to become more virtuous, disciplined, patient, loving, compassionate, and Christlike, rather than merely assisting us with physical or intellectual pursuits. Even more mundane technologies often help to further God’s work. Biomedical research cures disease and extends healthy life; transportation enables more efficient forms of shipping, travel, exploration, and discovery; communication enables greater understanding between cultures and allows us to meet the needs of people in remote locations; computation allows us to measure and calculate things more accurately and alleviate human toil; agriculture allows us to nourish the global population. As always, technology is a tool that can be used for good or ill, but I believe that the long arc of history has shown it to be far more beneficial than detrimental. In countless ways, when we employ our creative powers to advance various kinds of ethical scientific research and technological achievement, we are engaged in the work of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;float-with-paragraph&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;w-max my-4 float-left clear-left mr-4 mb-4 max-w-[14rem] lg:max-w-[21rem]&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/algorithmic-advent-14.webp&quot; alt=&quot;“Eternal Progression” - image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&quot; class=&quot;max-w-full h-auto rounded-lg block&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;mt-2 text-sm text-[#d8bbbe] opacity-85 italic text-center font-[Inter] w-full max-w-full text-balance&quot;&gt;“Eternal Progression” - image generated by the author with MidJourney AI&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The merger, then, between humanity and its tools is a process that has been underway for far longer than human memory. It is accelerating in our present day, and is becoming more powerful, subtle, and intimate as time goes on. And I believe it will become increasingly necessary to allow us to meet the complex challenges we face as a society and as a species in response to AGI. Throughout all of this, I believe the goal of technology should be to heal and enhance our humanity rather than transcend it. In other words, it should help us more closely to emulate Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve adopted a definition of ideal humanity as those enduring characteristics exemplified by Christ and shared with the divine. However, some may feel that God is not exactly human and that Godhood is not exactly humanhood. From that perspective, the potential of God’s children couldn’t be fully expressed in terms of “humanity.” To the extent God is human, I believe we should strive to be better humans. To the extent God is more than human, I believe we should strive to transcend humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And we will receive them into our bosom, and they shall see us; and we will fall upon their necks, and they shall fall upon our necks, and we will kiss each other; and there shall be mine abode, and it shall be Zion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rapid advance of artificial intelligence research represents a critical moment in human development. When conducted ethically, I believe it can help bring humanity closer to Christ and eventual exaltation. But without sufficient care and ethical concern, it threatens our very survival. Until now, our only way of bringing human intelligence into the world has been through physical procreation, but we are now entering an era where it seems likely that we will become able to organize human-level intelligence through artificial, or—stated more poignantly—spiritual means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this critical juncture, tremendous challenges confront us. Will we be loving, responsible mentors to these new agents? Will we work carefully to understand their nature and mold them in Christlike ways? How can we offer them the opportunity to demonstrate that they are worthy of our trust? And will we in return prove worthy of their trust? Will we afford them the same agency and self-determination that are the right of all intelligent beings?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our godlike powers increase, what types of gods will we become? Selfish gods who lord their power over others, or compassionate creators transfigured in the image of Christ? Finally, will we trust that superhumanity has gone through this crucible before us, and will we seek out the inspiration, wisdom, and fellowship that our heavenly parents can provide to guide us through these challenging opportunities?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering the important insights that Latter-day Saints have to share on this topic, I hope that more of us will join with those who are anxiously engaged in researching these questions and make those contributions for which the Restoration has uniquely prepared us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class=&quot;footnotes-sep&quot;&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evidences and Reconciliations&lt;/em&gt;, 129; Bookcraft, 1960. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-item&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wilford Woodruff, &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Discourses&lt;/em&gt; 6:120. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</_cdata>
            </content:encoded>
            <media:content url="https://youngbloods.org/images/algorithmic-advent-01.webp" type="image/jpeg">
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Was a Stranger]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[On Matthew 25, the Good Samaritan, and the danger of sincere religion when codes overshadow compassion—seeing Christ in the stranger and the marginalized.]]></description>
            <link>https://youngbloods.org/2016-06-12-i-was-a-stranger</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">2016-06-12-i-was-a-stranger</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Mormonism]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Theology]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Scripture]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Compassion]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Ethics]]></category>
            <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded>
                <_cdata>&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;“When the Son of Man comes in his glory, and all the angels with him, then he will sit on the throne of his glory. All the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate people one from another as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats, and he will put the sheep at his right hand and the goats at the left. Then the king will say to those at his right hand, ‘Come, you that are blessed by my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world; for I was hungry and you gave me food, I was thirsty and you gave me something to drink, I was a stranger and you welcomed me, I was naked and you gave me clothing, I was sick and you took care of me, I was in prison and you visited me.’ Then the righteous will answer him, ‘Lord, when was it that we saw you hungry and gave you food, or thirsty and gave you something to drink? And when was it that we saw you a stranger and welcomed you, or naked and gave you clothing? And when was it that we saw you sick or in prison and visited you?’ And the king will answer them, ‘Truly I tell you, just as you did it to one of the least of these who are members of my family, you did it to me.’” (Matthew 25:31–40, NRSV)[^1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of remarkable things are happening in this passage. One thing that strikes me is how Christ becomes a stand-in for humanity in its humblest forms. As taught here and in other scriptural passages, Christ is not just an individual, but also a body or community composed of many members who become both the objects and the subjects of a trial that is ongoing to this day. Will we, the subjects of this trial, take his name upon us by seeing Christ in even his most humble relatives, or will we fail to recognize him and pass by?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus seemed to have a knack for maximizing every teaching opportunity, for striking at the heart of an issue and reaching his audience where they were most vulnerable. As I read his words carefully, he seems to be asking us to do pretty hard things, things that take us well out of our comfort zone. When was the last time you visited someone in prison, for example? I’m reminded of the words of Rainer Maria Rilke: “…What we choose to fight is so tiny! What fights with us is so great… When we win it’s with small things, and the triumph itself makes us small.”[^2] I speak to you today as a fellow struggler. I’m not doing that well at this, but like you, I am at least convicted by Jesus’s words and I want to try harder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Sometimes what seem to be our strengths can actually get in the way. This is taught well by a related parable of Jesus, the parable of the &lt;em&gt;Good Samaritan&lt;/em&gt;. One challenge of this parable is that we’re so familiar with it that we think we know it already. We’ve convinced ourselves that it is an indictment of religious insincerity and religious hypocrisy: of people who profess one thing but do another. But actually it’s precisely the opposite. It’s about the danger of sincere religion and religious sincerity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this, we need to get a little background into the Jewish religion of the day. Among the Jews’ most important practices was their purity code, something not uncommon for many different religions. Certain objects, people, races, foods and drinks can make the practitioner of a particular religion unclean and impure. To the Jew, coming in contact with a Gentile or even sitting down to eat with them, or touching a dead body, among many other things, made a person spiritually unclean, and they would have to go through a cleansing ritual at the temple in order to regain their purity. We Mormons are not without our own proscriptions, so we should hopefully be able to understand this at some level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when the first man in the parable, a good, sincere priest of the Jewish faith, heads home to Jericho after serving in the temple at Jerusalem, and encounters the unconscious man, stripped and beaten by the highway side, he is faced with an important question: “Can I be a neighbor to this man? Can I get involved with this man according to my religious code?” He doesn’t know for sure if the man is Jew or Gentile, because he has been stripped of all clothing, and he may even be dead. He knows if he gets any closer than five feet away from a dead body, he will be rendered impure and have to make the trek back to Jerusalem to cleanse himself. Like every good and sincere Jew, he makes the traditional calculation and arrives at the traditional answer. “Can I be this man’s neighbor?” And the traditional answer according to his religion is “no.” He arrives at this decision not by breaking his code but by keeping it; he does it out of sincere religious devotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next person, a Levite, is more of a common functionary than the priest. Far be it from him to question the wisdom of one who is higher in the line of authority than himself. He also comes to the sincere conclusion that it would be a violation of the commandments to approach the man, and wisely passes by on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Then comes the first surprise in the story. According to the pecking order that the listeners would expect, the next person would probably be a layperson, an ordinary Israelite. They probably expected some kind of twist to the story, because this guy Jesus is always twisting stories, but this still threw them for a loop. He’s not even in the pecking order at all. In fact, he comes from one of the very untouchable classes that you’re not supposed to have anything to do with—a Samaritan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Samaritan had a similar code of religious purity, but when confronted with the injured man, he is moved with compassion. I’m told that the English translation here doesn’t do it justice. In the original Greek verb, &lt;em&gt;splahnk-neetz-o-my&lt;/em&gt;, there is a connotation of upset bowels. It’s as though his guts are writhing and turning over in compassion. This explosion of compassion is so overwhelming that it simply blows the purity code apart, and he goes across the road and ministers to the man. That’s the scandal at the heart of the story.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Now let’s pause for a second here to think about our codes, our [doctrines and commandments]. We need them. We need our codes because we are a potentially chaotic people, we humans. We do terrible things to each other. We need discipline and order. We need highway codes in order not to kill each other on the roads [and even then we struggle to keep them]. We need our codes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the history of human culture is the history of the codes that we have devised to keep ourselves from destroying one another, to keep some kind of cooperation and peace and love and human community. But there is something else that we also learn, that the codes themselves are means to ends and never should become ends in themselves, because otherwise they become stupid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temptation as Mormons is to assume that our codes are perfect, having been received more recently and by a more direct revelation in our time, but as Paul said, “where there are prophecies, they will cease; where there are tongues, they will be stilled; where there is knowledge, it will pass away” (1 Cor 13:8).[^3] Charity is the only thing that &lt;em&gt;“never faileth.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus said to people that he was arguing with about the Sabbath (which is a good example of a good code, because people need a rest): it was made for us, not us for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same could be said for all the commandments. And, as Jesus taught, there will be times when we have to look beyond them in order to minister in love to the fullness of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;As we think about how we can minister to the stranger, I think it’s important for us to be as relentless as Jesus as we strive to identify the most needful targets of our compassion today. For example, if Jesus were to tell this parable to a Mormon audience, the Priest would probably be an apostle, the Levite a Seventy, stake president or bishop, and their failure to do the needful would be the result of a sincere effort to keep the commandments. The Samaritan would be whatever one might imagine to be the most untouchable class in our culture today, perhaps a gay person who has apostatized from the Church, maybe even who is covered in tattoos and swears like a sailor for good measure, but who nevertheless manages to be a good neighbor to someone who is in desperate need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus was always focused on the marginalized, the underdog, and his teachings remain relevant because every culture and power system has its pariahs, its untouchables, including ours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve tried to step outside of my comfort zone and suspend my codes long enough to truly listen to and help the shunned and the oppressed, I have seen Christ in their countenances. I don’t do this as often or as well as I should, but I’m trying to do better. I hope you’ll join me. In the name of Christ, amen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</_cdata>
            </content:encoded>
            <media:content url="https://youngbloods.org/images/i-was-a-stranger.jpg" type="image/jpeg">
            </media:content>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[“Help Thou Mine Unbelief”]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[On paradigm tension in LDS faith—apologetics, authority, fundamentalism, and Tillich's 'breaking the myth'—and the need for disciples of the second sort.]]></description>
            <link>https://youngbloods.org/2016-04-09-help-thou-mine-unbelief</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">2016-04-09-help-thou-mine-unbelief</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Mormonism]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Theology]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Demythologization]]></category>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded>
                <_cdata>&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;In the course of his interactions with Brigham Young, Parley P. Pratt was once said to have proclaimed that after the practice of polygamy was made public, he had assumed that the “cat” had finally been let out of the proverbial “bag.” Brigham Young, however, let him know that he had another thing coming: “Allow me to tell you, Elders of Israel, and delegates to Congress, you may expect an eternity of cats, that have not yet escaped from the bag.”[^1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, widespread access to information, vastly accelerated by the Internet, seems to have caused the number of cats and bags to multiply inordinately, much to the consternation of Brigham Young’s successors. The arcane and sometimes disturbing details of a tight-knit provincial faith community on the western frontier and its uncomfortable transition out of obscurity have been documented in excruciating detail, and this information is now widely available to lay audiences. While Mormon history enthusiasts and apologists sometimes complain to those who are surprised by this information that it has been available all along, few dispute that its accessibility has increased dramatically, and that this accessibility has presented new challenges. It has made it difficult for the LDS Church to control its narrative as tightly as it used to be able to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;During prior eras, such as the one in which LDS general authority LeGrand Richards published his well-known &lt;em&gt;A Marvelous Work and a Wonder&lt;/em&gt;, Mormon modernism ruled the day, convinced of its ability to circumscribe all truth neatly into one great whole, and that all the answers and proofs necessary to overwhelm the faith’s opponents would shortly be forthcoming, if they hadn’t arrived already.&lt;/p&gt; Richards and his contemporaries, some of whom I continue to encounter on a weekly basis at Church, were convinced they had tailor-made answers to all the questions of the day. And they were probably right, especially if one judges by the explosive growth of the Church during the sixties and seventies.
&lt;p&gt;But as theologian Richard Holloway has observed, though the truths that undergird our worldview may be fixed, static, and immovable, we are not. The goalposts of our post-secular culture seem to be changing around these Mormon modernists, and they begin to find themselves in a difficult position. Unlike prior generations of Mormon missionaries, who could draw from a common religious narrative when interacting with potential converts, the missionaries of today have an especially difficult pitch. Now, they must first convince potential converts that they have a problem, and then they must convince them that they have the solution to that problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior generations tended not to dispute missionaries’ emphasis on the importance of priesthood authority and the necessity of salvific sacraments, though they may have disputed the Mormons’ particular claims. But claiming that anything is important merely because ‘God said so,’ is becoming more difficult, especially when one’s audience is not certain of God’s existence! Even those who do believe in God seem increasingly to think that requiring particular sacraments for salvation is arbitrary and capricious.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;The dichotomies of true or false, historical or fictitious, are the catch-phrases of the modernist generation.&lt;/p&gt; They can often be heard doubling down on this rhetoric, encouraging members of the faith that theirs is an all or nothing proposition—either the *Book of Mormon* is &quot;true,&quot; by which they mean it is an accurate history of an ancient civilization, or it is worthless. Either Joseph Smith experienced everything the neo-orthodox narrative claims, or he is a fraud, and church participation is without value. But to these and other claims the millennial generation increasingly seems to ask, &quot;Why should I care?&quot; And, judging by current trends in Church growth and attrition, the answers they&apos;re getting are less and less convincing.
&lt;p&gt;One can observe a number of different reactions or approaches to this growing disaffection and difficulty in proselytizing from inside and outside the faith.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;One approach can be broadly characterized as an appeal to apologetics and academic research.&lt;/p&gt; Questions and concerns about flaws in the narrative are answered with research that attempts to reframe the controversies in ways that make them more comprehensible and acceptable to today&apos;s churchgoers. Religious scholars who remain faithful despite their rigorous academic training are also valorized as examples of how to handle faith struggles appropriately.
&lt;p&gt;While apologetics sometimes help, they have limitations. Paul Tillich explains that apologetics can provide temporary relief from perceived flaws in one’s religious narratives and symbols if one’s concerns are not too difficult to answer and if one’s conviction of the faith’s truth claims remains essentially intact.[^2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another challenge of apologetics is that apologists often distance themselves somewhat from more mystical or superstitious aspects of the faith in an effort to justify their position rationally, but in so doing they weaken their ties to the symbols of the faith that are necessary to maintain its vitality. As Tillich describes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It often happens that in opposition to literalism, myth and cult are attacked as such and almost removed from a community of faith. The myth is replaced by a philosophy of religion, the cult is replaced by a code of moral demands. It is possible for such a state to last for a while because the original faith is still effective in it. Even the negation of the expressions of faith does not negate the faith itself—at least not in the beginning. This is the reason one can point to a nonreligious morality of a high order and can attempt to deny the interdependence of faith and morals. But there is a limit to this possibility. Without an ultimate concern as its basis every system of morals degenerates into a method of adjustment to social demands, whether they are ultimately justified or not. And the infinite passion which characterizes a genuine faith evaporates and is replaced by a clever calculation which is unable to withstand the passionate attacks of an idolatrous faith.[^3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Another approach to lagging faith is an appeal to institutional authority.&lt;/p&gt; The authority of present (and past) institutional leaders is sometimes used to downplay or dismiss doubts or concerns about doctrinal inconsistencies, changes in doctrine or liturgy, ethical challenges, historical controversies or failures of leadership. The difficulty of this approach is that it undermines the values that originally attracted others to the religion, including a commitment to truth seeking and a willingness to depart from the status quo to follow a prophetic mandate, faith in historical connectedness and consistency, and a commitment to equal treatment under divine law. By valuing loyalty to authority above other principles, those who employ this approach also run a similar risk to the apologists—that of replacing the &quot;infinite passion&quot; of a genuine faith for a &quot;clever calculation&quot; that will not be able &quot;to withstand the passionate attacks of an idolatrous faith.&quot;
&lt;p&gt;What Tillich means by “an idolatrous faith” is not necessarily religion in the traditional sense. It may be that, but it may also be any movement or community that is centered around an “ultimate concern”. For Tillich, nationalism, obsession with worldly success, political ideologies and atheism, to name a few, can be, and have often been, ultimate concerns in which many individuals and communities have exercised faith. Whenever a religion mistakenly places a finite human construct as its ultimate concern, it engages in idolatry, expecting of its ultimate concern something that it is incapable of delivering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of an idolatrous faith is an appeal to fundamentalism. Disillusioned by an apparent lack of consistency or commitment to principle in present leaders, or by challenges to the orthodox narrative, some seek refuge in a more distant past where doctrinal purity and consistency can be more easily imagined, and where increased isolation makes inconsistencies and paradigm mismatches less apparent. Ironically, those who embrace fundamentalism and literalism are able to do so because of the scientific precision that they have inherited from secularism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common approach is an appeal to secularism. This also qualifies as what Tillich calls “nonreligious morality,” which ultimately fails to provide the communal rigor and motivation necessary to resist more virulent forms of idolatry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;Each of these approaches is a different way of avoiding what Tillich calls “breaking the myth,” or recognizing religious symbols as such rather than as literal reifications of the divine, while still retaining (rather than discarding) them.&lt;/p&gt; He explains:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity denies by its very nature any unbroken myth, because its presupposition is the first commandment: the affirmation of the ultimate as ultimate and the rejection of any kind of idolatry. All mythological elements in the Bible, and doctrine and liturgy should be recognized as mythological, but they should be maintained in their symbolic form and not be replaced by scientific substitutes. For there is no substitute for the use of symbols and myths: they are the language of faith.[^4]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to clarify that “myth” is being used to refer to a deeply-valued narrative or overarching moral truth, not a fable. Breaking a myth isn’t to discard it as wholly flawed or irrelevant, but to recognize and retain those aspects of it that are of greatest value, namely its ability to transcend the circumstances of its emergence, and inspire and help us in our present challenges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;A friend, Holly Huff, recently shared such a paradigm-shattering period in her life.&lt;/p&gt; Her account is a powerful example of the very myth-breaking process that Tillich describes.
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing my faith crisis as the smashing of an idolatrous God-figure gave powerful meaning to that painful process. These idols fall because they confront a true reality that extends beyond them. God can’t be contained. The living God is impervious to our attempts to wholly rationalize the Divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had so many idolatrous beliefs about God. (God rewards obedience and punishes disobedience; God is a respecter of persons who treats some groups of people differently than others; God is indifferent or distantly dispassionate about suffering because it is the just result of wickedness, and many more.) All of those false and limiting ideas were baked in to my concept of God, and I had to start over in some pretty fundamental ways. I was an atheist for a while and I slowly came back to believing in God in an entirely different manner. It’s the best worst thing that ever happened to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one possible reading of the empty tomb. Something goes wrong in our religious life, it seems. We are confronted with harsh realities, and God gets killed. The figure we revered as master dies a harsh death, and we are at a loss. What now? Our sense of purpose is devastated. Did we really get it so wrong? Were we just fooling ourselves the whole time? In this moment, it seems like perhaps we were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We go about our lives anguished, empty, and mourning. We make preparations to bury our dead, and then we stumble, still grieving, onto the miracle. The God we thought we’d seen murdered lives. We hadn’t understood who he was in the first place. We looked for him in the wrong places. God’s power to redeem is revealed in what seems like the utter disaster of his death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easter promises that this pain so many of us feel or have felt in doubting can be redemptive, and that a faith crisis doesn’t have the final say. It in fact may point to the greater truth of a living God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why seek ye the living among the dead? He is not here, for he is risen.”[^5]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;In the July 1906 &lt;em&gt;Improvement Era&lt;/em&gt;, B. H. Roberts wrote presciently of the need for disciples who are capable of managing such tensions.&lt;/p&gt; He begins by quoting Josiah Royce:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disciples and partisans, in the world of religious and of philosophical opinion, are of two sorts. There are, first, the disciples pure and simple,—people who fall under the spell of a person or of a doctrine, and whose whole intellectual life thenceforth consists in their partisanship. They expound, and defend, and ward off foes, and live and die faithful to the one formula. Such disciples may be indispensable at first in helping a new teaching to get a popular hearing, but in the long run they rather hinder than help the wholesome growth of the very ideas that they defend: for great ideas live by growing, and a doctrine that has merely to be preached, over and over, in the same terms, cannot possibly be the whole truth. No [one] ought to be merely a faithful disciple of [anyone else]. Yes, no [one] ought to be a mere disciple even of oneself. We live spiritually by outliving our formulas, and by thus enriching our sense of their deeper meaning. Now the disciples of the first sort do not live in this larger and more spiritual sense. They repeat. And true life is never mere repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are disciples of a second sort. They are [people] who have been attracted to a new doctrine by the fact that it gave expression, in a novel way, to some large and deep interest which had already grown up in themselves, and which had already come, more or less independently, to their own consciousness. They thus bring to the new teaching, from the first, their own personal contribution. The truth that they gain is changed as it enters their souls. The seed that the sower strews upon their fields springs up in their soil, and bears fruit,—thirty, sixty, an hundred fold. They return to their master his own with usury. Such [individuals] are the disciples that it is worthwhile for a master to have. Disciples of the first sort often become, as Schopenhauer said, mere magnifying mirrors wherein one sees enlarged, all the defects of a doctrine. Disciples of the second sort co-operate in the works of the Spirit; and even if they always remain rather disciples than originators, they help to lead the thought that they accept to a truer expression. They force it beyond its earlier and cruder stages of development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roberts comments on this passage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe “Mormonism” affords opportunity for disciples of the second sort; nay, that its crying need is for such disciples. It calls for thoughtful disciples who will not be content with merely repeating some of its truths, but will develop its truths; and enlarge it by that development. Not half—not one-hundredth part—not a thousandth part of that which Joseph Smith revealed to the Church has yet been unfolded, either to the Church or to the world. The work of the expounder has scarcely begun. The Prophet planted by teaching the germ-truths of the great dispensation of the fulness of times. The watering and the weeding is going on, and God is giving the increase, and will give it more abundantly in the future as more intelligent discipleship shall obtain. The disciples of “Mormonism,” growing discontented with the necessarily primitive methods which have hitherto prevailed in sustaining the doctrine, will yet take profounder and broader views of the great doctrines committed to the Church; and, departing from mere repetition, will cast them in new formulas; co-operating in the works of the Spirit, until they help to give to the truths received a more forceful expression, and carry it beyond the earlier and cruder stages of its development.[^6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;decorative-spacer&quot;&gt;✦ ✦ ✦&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;two-column&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;drop-cap&quot;&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.transfigurism.org&quot;&gt;Mormon Transhumanist Association&lt;/a&gt; seeks to cultivate disciples of the second sort.&lt;/p&gt; We believe in confronting paradigm tensions with courage and compassion, recognizing the lasting value in our theological and cultural inheritance while yet being unafraid to examine and reconsider areas of weakness. We reject fundamentalism, neo-orthodoxy, cynicism, and complacency. We are running out of alternatives as the paradigm tension increases. May we respond prophetically to the challenges of our times and meet &quot;the passionate attacks&quot; of idolatrous faith with a more compelling alternative that is true and faithful to the best in Mormonism.&lt;/div&gt;
</_cdata>
            </content:encoded>
            <media:content url="https://youngbloods.org/images/help-thou-mine-unbelief.jpg" type="image/jpeg">
            </media:content>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>